Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 3 -- Letters to Franklin 1778 April-December Mss.B.F85inventory03
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Anticipates a winter in London with much pleasure. Suggestions concerning the trade carried on for his brother.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 November 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Smith, Dr. James. Paris
    A list of his possessions detained at Calais; it depends upon the Commissioners whether the custom house officers shall be allowed to defraud him; desires a pass for himself and family in England, and hopes his frank expression of opinion will not influence their refusal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 15; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Brillon, Monsieur
    Sends Dr. Franklin the "Eripuit coelo fulmen, sceptrumque tyrannis," a new composition in his honor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 15; L.S. 2p.; Berry, William et al
    Appeal of seven American prisoners confined at Dinan, France, asking Franklin to obtain their release.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 16; A.L.S. 3p.; de Beze,-----. Tannay
    Begging for news of M. de Fleury, who entered the American service, and, according to the published accounts, has greatly distinguished himself; for two years his family have heard nothing from him; begs for any news of him he may possess.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 16; L.S. 2p.; La Plaigne, Emmanuel-Pierre de. Dunkirk
    Will arrive in Paris with his brother and servant; his brother-in-law, his nephew and two of his relatives have already set out; his brother given a lieutenancy by the Congress of Georgia; the others go as volunteers; acknowledges the sum received from Mr. Coffyn to defray their expenses to Plymouth; very anxious to get back to his regiment.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 November 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Gilbank, John. Nantes
    No answer to his letters, is obliged to trouble him a third time for money to enable him to rejoin his regiment; his deplorable situation should Franklin refuse.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 17; L.S. 2p.; Jullian, Charles Nicolas. Cette
    His strong desire to go to America, a step which he hesitates to take without the assurance of Franklin's recommendation and protection.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 November 17; A.L.S. 3p.; Gilbank, John. Nantes
    Takes exception to the statement that it would be blameable partiality to lend more to him than to others of the same rank; makes certain claims as a Continental Commissioned Officer, and begs again for the desired sum.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Prince, Job. "The Concord," off Dieppe
    Has been appointed by Congress to the command of the "Concord"; desires advice as to his intended cruise, as well as directions as to the disposal of possible prizes. Being fired upon by an English frigate, he threw overboard the despatches from Congress. Has something of great importance to communicate which he will not trust to paper.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Le Baron, ------. Dieppe
    Account of the provisions with which he supplied Captain Job Prince, of the "Concord"; asks for an authorized commission as American agent. Advisability of sending a small French corsair as pilot for the Concord.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    M. Montieu's generous offer; merely desires security in case of his death; asks Franklin to furnish this. Arrival of his uncle.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Kermorvan, Chevalier de
    The Queen of France has given birth to a daughter; such a joyful occasion is auspicious for the asking and granting of favors, therefore begs Franklin to write a line, on his behalf, to the Minister of War.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 19; L.S. 1p.; Mounier and Denis. Middelburg
    Concerning the capture of their vessel by the Americans who carried her to New England; applies for her freedom, payment for her cargo and indemnity for the time lost.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Du Belair, -----. Paris
    Is obliged to leave Paris; M. Bardinet, author of the poem on The Defenders of Liberty, desires to pay his respects in person and obtain his opinion of the poem.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Cadou fils (merchants). Nantes
    Concerning a plan for which he hopes to have the approval of Franklin and his friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 20; A.L.S. 1p.; de Butler, Otto Magnus. Axel
    Desires to enter the service of America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Valmont de Bomare, Jacques-Christophe
    Desires to dine with him at Mme. de Chaumont's; also begs his presence on December 3d at his opening lecture and at a small philosophical dinner.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 November 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    The despotic act consummated in the Provincial Assembly and the Admiralty Report passed; Amsterdam's vigorous protest against this procedure; eager for news from America which may give the lie to certain rumors.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 20; D.S. 3p.; Walsh, John et al., on Board the "Drake." Brest Road
    Memorial of English prisoners on board the brig "Patience" asking for better treatment.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 November 20; L.S. 1p.; Middleton, Thomas. Philadelphia
    Has lost two bills of exchange drawn on the Commissioners for interest due him on money lent the public; stops their payment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Recommending Mr. Duncan Ingraham who goes to France on business in his own vessel.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 November 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Report on the cannon belonging to M. Le Bertin; the expense of proving them. Kindness of M. de La Touche in ordering a frigate to escort the ships round from La Rochelle to Nantes where they are being loaded.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Bottin, -----. St. Quentin
    Is a surgeon and has discovered a specific remedy for all kinds of fevers. Has heard that the King has offered rewards to those who can prove that they have discovered useful and efficacious remedies. Wishes to go to Paris to demonstrate the efficacy of his remedy and asks to be assisted in accomplishing his purpose.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 21; Mem. 3p.; -----,-----. Belfast
    Memorial from several residents of Belfast, Ireland, who wish to settle in the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Genet, Edme Jacques, d.1781
    Desires Franklin to authorize his denial of the statement that after the capture of Burgoyne's army, Washington told the Congress it was the happy time to treat.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Bottin, -----. St. Quentin
    Has invented a certain specific which he has found efficacious in fevers and epidemics; has heard that the King of France promises a reward for such discoveries in proportion to their effectiveness; desires to know when he shall come to Paris to furnish proof of this remedy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Dubois, abbé -----. Nancy
    Interest in America all over France; universal admiration of her conduct; no republic ever had a more auspicious birth; the immortal name of Franklin and the honor which will be paid to it by future generations.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Guichard,-----, ainé. Marennes
    Writes again to demand a sum due his brother for his services on board the "Lexington"; indignantly protests against the silence with which his former letters have been received.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Jesse Taylor. Belfast
    Enclosing a memorial, the subject of which may have already reached Franklin in an interview with Sir Edward Newenham; reasons for withholding their signatures; many adventurers only waiting for information as to how to avoid the present dangers of such a voyage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 22; A.L.S. 3p.; D' Aire, ------. Alby
    Desires to enter the American army; is willing to serve as volunteer until the American generals consider him worthly to be given the command of a force.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Capt. Thomas Pickerin. Brest
    Protesting against the action of Captain [John Paul] Jones with regard to deserters from American vessels.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Ridley, Matthew. Nantes
    The manuscripts in the hands of J. Massey have been disposed of some time since. The disposition of the Ministry is evidently to try another campaign in America. Clinton's proceedings in burning and destroying perfectly consistent with the ideas of war; their attitude unchanged by the loss of Dominica.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Enclosing copy of a letter (2p.) from Arthur Lee, together with his reply (2p., in French), concerning a loan which Mr. Lee says he is empowered to obtain as secretly as possible for the United States; slightly prepared for this by the former negotiations between Mr. Wm. Lee and M.de Neufville; desires Franklin's opinion of this step.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 24; A.L.S. 2p.; La Cadette, Romaneix. Limoges
    Requesting Franklin's protection for his brother who made his escape from the hands of the English without clothing or money; has lent him all he can afford.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Bordot, L. Versailles
    Begs Franklin to forward to America the enclosed letter from Madame de Rivaud, who is full of anxiety about her son from whom she has not heard for a long time.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Monchy, Solomon de (François' father). Rotterdam
    Recalls their acquaintance during Franklin's and Dr. Pringle's stay at Rotterdam. Asks Franklin's protection for a vessel, the property of his son-in law, Jacob Mounier, which was taken by an American privateer and carried to New England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Is the bearer of many affectionate messages from the Comtesse de Forbach. The many losses in commercial enterprises; thinks the Royal Marine have done all they could to protect the ships; advises the publication in the papers of a list of prizes taken by the Americans; thinks such a step will have a salutary effect.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 November 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    The merchants, owing to their heavy losses, are obliged to cut down their exports to the United States. Preparation of a fine convoy for the two ships at Nantes. Report confirmed as to M. La Motte Picquet having fallen into the hands of a Jamaica fleet. Action of the Farmers General as regards tobacco.
  - to Messrs. Franklin and Adams., 1778 November 28; L.S. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    Not having any notice of their altered plans, he and Count de Vergennes waited for them in vain till five O'Clock. The Count wishes to know just when the ships will ready to sail, so that he may do all in his power to obtain the desired convoy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 Novermber 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Cadet, -----
    Desires his presence the next day at M. Dubourg's; wishes his fireplace to be a success, and doubts not that Franklin's advice will insure this result.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 November 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Gilbank, John. Nantes
    Mr. Livingston sails in six days; cannot go with him unless his former request for money is compiled with.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 29; A.L.S. 1p.; d'Aubigne, Marquis. Passy
    Desires information concerning the purchase of American bills of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Roumallard, ----- Perdriel. Mortrée
    Desires to know if Franklin has received any letters from Congress for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Baron,---- Le. Dieppe
    Believes the pretended corsair, the "Concord," will not appear again; she gained little from her deception; advisability of having a letter from Franklin for the pretended Captain, Job Prince, in case he should return to seek an answer to his letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 30; A.L.S. 4p.; D'Amblé, Abbé. La Claireau
    A plan of establishing well-equipped forges and arsenals in pennsylvania; question of bringing the workmen over from France; his knowledge of this industry.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Masseure, Francis-Geron. St. Malo
    Announcing his capture by the enemy and his destruction of the packet sent by Patrick Henry to Franklin; his subsequent escape and desire to return to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Amiel, Charlotte. Auteuil
    Begs Franklin not to suffer her husband to remain longer in suspense as to the outcome of his business at Brest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778 before Nov. 30] Saturday morning; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Sends for a letter which Franklin wishes to be delivered to M. Le Veillard. Has been very ill for some days.
  - to The American Commissioners., After [1778 November 17]; A.L.S. 4p.; Smith, Dr James
    Their extraordinary reply to his requst for a passport, is told that he must take the oath of allegiance; denounces such conduct as infamous.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 1; L.S. 1p.; Gleed, Thomas et al. Combourg
    Six English prisoners appeal to Franklin to be included in the next exchange of French and English prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 1; A.L.S. 1p.; de Vienne, Field Marshall Comte. Paris
    Asks that the enclosed letter to his son, the Marquis de Vienne, may be forwarded to America; his son complains that, though he has received the rank of colonel, his services, in other respects, have not been suitably recognized; begs Franklin to recommend him in his letters to Congress and to General Washington.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 1; L.S. 2p.; Meunier,------. Paris
    Desires to deliver the memoir of Messieurs Risteau, of Bordeaux; hopes their reasons will determine Captain McNeill to finish an affair, which has lasted too long.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 1; A.L.S. 4p.; Holtzer, Antoine. Colmar
    Has invented a new variety of beer, which has remarkable advantages; is willing to sell his secret.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Enclosing a copy of Amsterdam's Resolutions, è propos of increasing the army in Holland (22 p.); intrigues of the English party aim to increase the army of Holland at the expense of her navy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 2; A.L.S. 8p.; Weiss de Daillens, —. Berne
    His harred of oppression and tyranny; his ardent desire to serve under the standard of liberty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Turner, Thomas. Croisic
    Wishes to know if his father, Captain Thomas Turner, is in the American service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Maire de Gimel, Jacques. Nantes
    Reiterates his request for an answer to the Governor of Virginia's letter, also for a recommendation in favor of M. Doumolon; offers to carry any despatches Franklin cares to intrust to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Thiery, -----. Paris
    Concerning two bills of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Gates, Horatio. Boston
    Chevalier de Raimondis, late Captain of the "Cæsar," one of Comte d'Estaing's squadron, had the misfortune to lose his arm in an engagement off the coast; his subsequent stay in Boston, and the presentation to him by the Council fo Massachusetts of a fine sword; hopes he will be generously rewarded for his sufferings and heroic behavior. The enemy likely to evacuate New York and Rhode Island.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Farley, Henry. Paris
    Concerning a general order, forbidding British subjects to settle in French sea-ports; begs that he and Mr. Thompson's two sons may be permitted to reside unmolested at Nantes, being convinced that his commercial interest will be of general advantage to France and America; his and Mr. Thompson's strong sentiments in favor of the country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Clark, Elisha. Bolbec
    Enclosing a letter from Dr. Williams, of London, and begging Franklin's compliance with his request.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    News of Count d'Estaing's fleet; report prevails that Admiral Byron's fleet left New York, November 2d with 5,000 troops on board. The Boston, Providence and Ranger arrived at Boston with many prizes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Vernon, William. Boston
    Informs him that his son, who is just out of the University and whose talent is scarcely known, took passage for France with Mr. John Adams, under whose care he placed him, with a view to accomplish him for business either as a merchant or in any other way, that he might be most useful in the future to his country. Hopes he may regard him as one of his friends and that he will, from time to time, receive such advice and instructions from his friends as will stimulate him to virtue, honor and knowledge.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Another blow to the English party in the shape of the enclosed memoir (1 p.) from the French Ambassador, asking an explanation of Holland's future conduct and demanding the most perfect neutrality.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Lovell, James. Philadelphia
    Reasons for holding back his last letter to Franklin. The only important struggle is with the currency; the aid of skilful financiers and monied men needed to bring about any considerable appreciation.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Lee, William
    Conformable to the enclosed Resolution of Congress, has drawn upon them for a certain sum. Report of a Congress to be held between the Ministers from the Courts of Versailles and St. Petersburg, to arrange a reconciliation between the Emperor and the King of Prussia; also reported that Great Britain has prevailed on Russia to take advantage of this opportunity to negotiate an accommodation between France and Great Britain.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Sends the enclosed memorial from the prisoners on the "Patience"; their situation most deplorable and their complaints just; declares that Rivu, who has charge of them, is a scoundrel and begs them to send their answer through the Reverend Father John, as otherwise it will never reach the prisoners.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Gourlade and Moylan. L'Orient
    The arrival of the schooner "Dauphin," from Boston; brings news of the loss to England of the "Somerset" man-of-war, and the unfortunate capture of the frigate " Raleigh," after an obstinate engagement.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, David. London
    Concerning the exchange of prisoners; announcing the acceptance, by the Admiralty, of the last terms submitted by Franklin.
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, I, 211.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 10; Mem. 2p.; Denward, Thomas
    Urging the necessity of having an agent in London, amd recommending Captain Robinson for the position. Dietary for prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 10; L.S. 3p.; Greene, William. Warwick, R. I
    Enclosing some bills of exchange which he begs Franklin to lay out for him and his son-in law, Major Samuel Ward; the latter's desire to receive consignments of cargoes from merchants in France. Recommending to Franklin's kindness Mr. William Vernon, Jr., now in France for the purpose of studying the language. Family news.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Abercromby, John. Bordeaux
    Wrote three weeks ago concerning a passport to enable him to return to Charleston; begs him not to forget his request.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Polignac, Louis-Héraclius-Melchior, vicomte de. Soleure
    Recommending M.Weiss de Daillens.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 13; A.L.S. 4p.; de Randerath, Baronne. Bouquenom
    Her husband forced by illness to give up his service to the Elector Palatine; their small resources; impossible to take her huband to Aix; applies to franklin for assistance; places her hopes in the fact that her husand and Franklin are both Masons, though belonging to different lodges.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Gunnison, Benjamin. Roscoff
    Announcing his arrival in the brig, "Morris," and asking for instruction as to his future movements.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 14; L. 4p.; F-----, J -----. Heidelberg
    Submits proposal to raise a body of 240 volunteers to serve in the United States in the war of independence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Sube. A., Laporte, and others. Marseilles
    Recounting a féte, recently celebrated by the Société de Parnasse in honor of their good friends and allies, the insurgents; encloses a printed paper which will give him the proceedings in detail; Franklin's portrait, crowned with laurel, had the place of honor; the influence it exerted on the company.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 15; A.L.S. 4p.; Lee, William. Frankfort
    Has reason to believe that a plan of reconciliation between France and Great Britain will be agitated at the Congress mentioned in his last letter; suggests the advisability of having an agent there to counteract the schemes of Great Britain; has sounded a gentleman on the subject, at present in the service of the King of Prussia; and transcribes his answer; asks their opinion of his propositions; advises his going to the Congress as an authorized individual.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Conway, Françoise-Antoinette-Jeanne Langlois du Bouchet, comtesse de. Auxerre
    Desires news of her husband, of Franklin's health, and of the war in America; intends to call on him during the winter.
  - The American Commissioners., 1778 December 15; L.S. 2p.; D. Schweighauser, John, et al., Merchants at Nantes
    Hope, through the Commissioner's efforts, to secure a convoy for their vessels for the entire voyage across the Atlantic.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Extract from Mr. A. Lee's letter, heaping reproaches on Holland for her reluctance to aid the United States and threatening them with exclusion from future benefits; embarrassed how to tell him that he is ignorant of the state of the Republic and says what is neither just nor reasonable; explains the situation to Franklin; ask him to keep this letter secret.
  - The American Commissioners., 1778 December 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Gilbank, John. Nantes
    Complains of receiving no answer to his last letters; there is still time for him to rejoin his regiment, if his necessary expenses are defrayed at once; anguish of mind he suffers in such a humiliating situation, which has been brought about by the chance of war.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 16; A.L.S. 2p.; de Beaulieu, Chevalier. Paris
    Prophesies a magnificent future for America, and a deathless fame for Franklin; desires to serve this astonishing people.